Okay, today's דף daf is ה. Hey. We are a little behind.
We continue on דף ד עמוד ב. daf Dalet Amud Bet. We
had about ten lines from the top, eight lines from the top.
We had just seen a whole range of opinions about what is
the שיעור ביאה, shiur biah, the amount of time that it would
take to do the, even begin the act of intercourse. And one
of them used a metaphor about sticking a hand into a basket
with loaves of bread and quoted a פסוק. pasuk. So now we're
going to pick up on a דרשה, drasha, other דרשות drashot based
on this פסוק. pasuk. So the גמרא Gemara continues as follows, six
lines from the top. דרש רב אבירא זימנין אמר לה משמיה דרב
אמי וזימנין אמר לה משמיה דרב אסי. Darash Rav Avira zimnin amar
lah mishmei deRav Ammi vezimnin amar lah mishmei deRav Assi. Rav Avira
explicated, sometimes in the name of Rav Ammi, sometimes in the name
of Rav Assi. כל האוכל לחם בלא נטילת ידים כאילו בא על
אשה זונה. Kol ha'ochel lechem belo netilat yadayim ke'ilu ba al ishah
zonah. Whoever eats bread without washing his hands is as if he
had intercourse with a woman who is a
prostitute. שנאמר כי בעד אשה זונה עד ככר לחם. shene'emar ki be'ad
ishah zonah ad kikar lachem. Because on account of a woman who
is a prostitute, man is reduced to a loaf of bread. A
hard פסוק pasuk to exactly translate. So now we are saying that
because of how you treat a loaf of bread, it can be
like having intercourse with a prostitute. Obviously from the male perspective, it's
interesting, worth noting, you know, the oftentimes
analogy of eating, a certain appetite with sexuality, and that can be
done in a very holy context, you know, wash your hands, you
prepare for it with blessings and so on, sexuality within marriage, within
קדושה, kedusha, and it can be done in a way that is
just about self-pleasuring. So there's an interesting actually parallel here,
but the גמרא Gemara will discuss whether this is a reasonable read
of the פסוק. pasuk. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this. אמר רבא האי בעד אשה זונה עד ככר לחם בעד ככר
לחם אשה זונה מיבעי ליה. Amar Rava hai be'ad ishah zonah ad
kikar lachem be'ad kikar lachem ishah zonah mibei lei. The verse should
have been the reverse. Rather it should have said because of how
one is with a loaf of bread, that is like the how
one is being with a prostitute. The verse though had it phrased
the opposite. It starts with a relationship to a prostitute and then
it compares it to the loaf of bread. אלא אמר רבא. Ella
amar Rava. So Rava says here's how we're going to interpret the
verse. כל הבא על אשה זונה לבסוף מבקש ככר לחם. Kol haba
al ishah zonah lesof mevakesh kikar lachem. And which might actually be
very much the פשט pshat of the פסוק, pasuk, which is whoever
has intercourse with a prostitute, whoever is you know generally sleeps with
prostitutes, in the end they will become poor and they will go
around begging for a loaf of
bread. אמר רב
זריקא אמר רבי אלעזר כל המזלזל בנטילת ידים נעקר מן העולם.
Amar Rav Zreika amar
Rabbi Eleazar kol hamizalsel binetilat yadayim ne'ekar min ha'olam. So now that
we're talking about how one, washing one's hands before eating bread, and
people that are abiding by it or not abiding by it, we're
going to develop that topic for a little bit. So says Rav
Zreika in the name of Rabbi Eleazar, whoever treats lightly,
disparagingly, the need to wash one's hand before bread will be uprooted
from the world. That's a pretty harsh statement. אמר רב חייא בר
אשי אמר רב מים ראשונים צריך שיגביה ידיו למעלה מים אחרונים צריך
שישפיל ידיו למטה. Amar Rav Chiya bar Ashi amar Rav mayim rishonim
tzarich sheyagbi'ah yadav lemalah mayim achronim tzarich sheyashpil yadav lemata. When you
wash the water, the מים ראשונים mayim rishonim before eating bread, you
have to lift up your fingers. When you do the מים אחרונים,
mayim achronim, you have to have your fingers pointed down. Now let's
see what this is about. תניא נמי הכי הנוטל ידיו צריך שיגביה
ידיו למעלה. Tanya nami hachi hanotel yadav tzarich sheyagbi'ah yadav lemalah. We
taught similar to this, when you do נטילת ידים netilat yadayim before
eating bread, you have to lift your hands upwards, your fingers upwards.
שמא יצאו המים חוץ לפרק ויחזרו ויטמאו את הידים. Shema yetze'u hamayim
chutz laperek veyachzeru veyetame'u et hayadayim. Because we're afraid that the water
will go below the wrist and then come back on the fingers.
What does this mean? The reason one washes hands before eating bread
is because the כהנים Kohanim would eat their, would often eat תרומה,
terumah, their bread would be made out of תרומה terumah flour. And
תרומה terumah cannot become טמא. tamei. Now the rabbis established that your
hands would be considered a שני לטומאה. sheni letumah.
Without having washed them in general because you don't know where your
hands are up to, we consider them to be a second-degree derivative
of טומאה. tumah. Now what can that do? That can only make
something טמא tamei that is תרומה terumah or more holy. It cannot
make normal things טמא. tamei. So that was the concern for כהנים.
Kohanim. So כהנים Kohanim had to wash their hands, you know, the
same way they could make only the hands טמא, tamei, the rabbis
said that you could make the hands טהור tahor without going your
whole body into a מקוה, mikvah, and that would be done through
washing the hands. So they would do this ritual washing of the
hands in order to allow them to eat תרומה. terumah. And we
do it in parallel of that, you know, copying that as a
way of treating it because a, there would be people who would
eat normal bread as if it were תרומה terumah bread, and it's
a way of really bringing קדושה kedusha into our eating, as if
we are doing this same thing the כהנים Kohanim would do, would
be eating the תרומה terumah bread, which gets back to the גמרא
Gemara about bringing קדושה kedusha into the framing of our eating. So
why do we do it twice on the hands? Because the first
time, the מים ראשונים, mayim rishonim, the water gets the hands טהור,
tahor, but the water itself... comes in contact with the hands and
becomes טמא. Tamei. It actually becomes a ראשון, Rishon, that's a special
הלכה Halacha about liquids, even though a minute ago I said only
תרומה Trumah would be a problem, liquids are different. Now, let's say
you overdid it and some of that water spilled on and went
below your wrist
and
went on your forearm.
So the water becomes טמא. Tamei. Now, what happens? How does that
not become a problem? Well, that's why we do the second water.
The second water, the second pouring, makes the first water טהור. Tahor.
Right? You'll understand there are some logical problems like how come why
the water not sitting there can go back and make the hands
טמא. Tamei. That's not a problem, as long as you do the
second water. The concern though is that you will overdo it the
first time, you will pour the water and it will go outside
of the and below your wrist and then the second time it
will only go up to the wrist. So therefore there will be
water on your forearm that is טמא Tamei that has not become
טהור. Tahor. And now if you hold your hands down and that
water runs back on your hands, now you have made your hands
טמא. Tamei. That is the concern. By the way I should say
that I'm talking about the wrist and the forearm, there's another opinion
in the ראשונים Rishonim that what we're talking about is where the
fingers attach to the actual the second knuckle where they actually attach
to the palm. And that's a major question of course about how
do you do נטילת ידיים? Netilas Yadayim? Do you make sure it's
just your fingers or do you make sure it's your whole hand?
In general we try to follow the position that it's your whole
hand, but בשעת הדחק besha'as hadechak when you need to you can
follow the position that it is just the fingers. Anyway the point
is that if you let your fingers down it is possible there
will be טמא tamei water that runs back on your fingers, so
keep your fingers up. That's why we do it.
תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, so we taught similarly, הנוטל ידיו
צריך שיגביה ידיו למעלה, hanotel yadav tzarich sheyagbi'ah yadav lemalah, you have
to lift up your hands above, שמא יצאו המים חוץ לפרק, shema
yetzu hamayim chutz laperak, the waters will go outside below the joint,
whichever joint that is, the palm or the wrist, ויחזרו ויטמאו ידיים,
veyachzeru veyetam'u yadayim, and they did not become טהור tahor because they
didn't get the second waters on them and then they will be
make your hands טמא tamei again. So keep your fingers up. אמר
רבי אבהו, Amar Rabi Abahu, or just dry your hands really well.
And by the reason for the מים אחרונים mayim acharonim the fingers
are down is there you're trying to wipe away the מלח סדומית,
melach Sedomit, the salt and the smelly stuff so you want to
get it away from you and therefore you want your fingers down,
you want it to run down. אמר רבי אבהו, Amar Rabi Abahu,
כל האוכל פת בלא ניגוב ידיים כאילו אוכל לחם טמא. kol ha'ochel
pat belo niguv yadayim ke'ilu ochel lechem tamei. So we are going
now again to speaking about washing the hands but now the importance
of drying your hands. Okay, so if you eat it without drying,
technically your hands are טהור tahor as we said, but רב אסי
Rav Asi considers that to be something like not like a little
unseemly and disgusting and it's so unpalatable. So therefore he says that
is equivalent to as if it were still טמא. tamei.
So it says like this, כל האוכל פת בלא ניגוב כאילו אוכל
לחם טמא kol ha'ochel pat belo niguv ke'ilu ochel lechem tamei שנאמר
shene'emar ויאמר ה' ככה יאכלו בני ישראל את לחמם טמא. vayomer Hashem
kacha yochlu venei Yisrael et lachmam tamei. It's so the children of
Israel will eat their bread טמא tamei and it's not literally טמא,
tamei, it's something that is רש"י Rashi says מאוס, ma'us, like a
disgusting, and therefore disgusting is like it is ritually טמא tamei and
it's interesting like which one resonates more, ech don't do it it's
disgusting, don't do it it's טמא, tamei, for some people the sort
of ritual significance
will be more powerful than the don't do it it's disgusting. But
again this interesting thing about the proper approach to eating bread and
the analogy also about to sexuality. Okay, so let's take a
look. ומאי ואשת איש נפש יקרה תצוד. umai ve'eshet ish nefesh yekarah
tatzud. Now, the end of this פסוק pasuk from משלי Mishlei about
the loaf of bread and the prostitute says that a married woman
will capture a dear soul. So how would we explain that verse
in a homiletic way? אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן
Amar Rabi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabi Yochanan כל אדם שיש בו
גסות הרוח לבסוף נכשל באשת איש. kol adam sheyesh bo gasut haruach
levasof nichshal be'eshet ish. Whoever has
a haughtiness, literally like a heaviness or a thickness of the
wind, very haughty, in the end that person will think that they're
so wonderful that they can do whatever they want and therefore they
will sin with the in the sin of adultery with a married
woman. שנאמר ואשת איש נפש יקרה תצוד, shene'emar ve'eshet ish nefesh yekarah
tatzud, and a married woman a dear soul which here means like
a heavy soul or a haughty soul will
capture a married woman. You know, so that's actually interesting because it
echoes the פסוק pasuk back by נח Noach at the end of
פרשת נח, parshas Noach, excuse me the end of פרשת בראשית parshas
Bereishis leading into נח Noach where it says that when בני אלוקים
benei Elokim took בנות האדם. benot ha'adam. They just felt they could
have whatever they want and they would grab married women as חז"ל
Chazal understand it from right under the חופה. chuppah. No sense about
relationships and who is connected to who, you just feel it's all
entitled to it, you can do whatever you want. So that is
how the גמרא Gemara saying is the concern here not just any
sin but a sin that you're entitled to anything. אמר רבי חייא
בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן—oh, Amar Rabbi Chiya Bar Abba, Amar Rabbi
Yochanan we just said that, I'm sorry. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara
says אמר רבא, Amar Rava, now רבא Rava is, you know, like
he did before,
is not so concerned with how powerful the message is, but how
much it fits into the
פסוק. pasuk. האי נפש יקרה, נפש גבוהה מיבעי ליה. Hai nefesh yikara,
nefesh gevoha mi-ba'ei lei. I'm not saying a dear soul, it should
say a haughty soul, a high soul, if you know you want
to talk about somebody
haughty. ועוד היא תצוד מיבעי ליה. Ve-od hi tatzud mi-ba'ei lei. If
it's saying a married woman a haughty soul will capture, ensnare, it
should then have referred back to the married woman, היא תצוד, hi
tatzud, it will ensnare her. So the פסוק pasuk does not sound
like the way you want to read it. אלא אמר רבא, Ella
amar Rava, here's how to read
it: כל הבא על אשת איש, kol ha-ba al eshet ish, אפילו
למד תורה דכתיב בה יקרים מפנימים, afillu lamad Torah de-ktiv bei yekarim
mi-pnimim, even if he's a dear soul and he has learned תורה
Torah which is the dearest thing, it is dearer than
jewels, מכהן גדול שנכנס לפני ולפנים, mi-Kohen Gadol she-nichnas lifnai ve-lifnim, and
the classic דרשה drasha is even greater than the כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol who goes into the innermost
chambers. היא תצודנו לדינה של גיהנום. Hi titzudennu le-dina shel Gehennom. That
the married woman, the sin with that married woman, that will ensnare
him all the way to גיהנום. Gehennom. So he is not ensnaring
the woman, he is sinning with the woman and the
woman's—not the woman—the sin is ensnaring him. Okay, so that's how bad
that is. אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי שמעון בר יוחאי. Amar Rabbi
Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon Bar Yochai. Now because we've mentioned haughtiness of
soul, we're now going to have a long exposition about the problems
of haughtiness of soul, you know, just haughtiness. Pride cometh before the
fall and all of that. But it's interesting that the phrase is
גסות רוח gassut ruach because we cannot escape realizing that, you know,
the פסוק pasuk by סוטה, Sotah, right, is ועבר עליו רוח קנאה,
ve-avar alav ruach kinah, a spirit of jealousy. And the גמרא Gemara
had a discussion, was this a רוח ruach of, you know, was
this a מצוה? mitzvah? Was this a good רוח, ruach, of טומאה
tumah or of טהרה? taharah? And now talking about a רוח ruach
that is a, you know, גסות הרוח, gassut ha-ruach, makes one question,
you know, where is this jealousy coming from? Is this person just
a super jealous husband and anything he's jealous about and so on?
I think it really forces us to consider the relationship with גסות
הרוח gassut ha-ruach and this רוח קנאה. ruach kinah. So let's take
a look. Okay, so
אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי שמעון בר יוחאי: Amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum
Rabbi Shimon Bar Yochai: כל אדם שיש בו גסות רוח, kol adam
she-yesh bo gassut ruach, כאילו עובד עבודת כוכבים, ke-illu oved avodat kochavim,
it's as if they worshipped idols because then you're not humble to
anybody, you're not humble to God, you are your own authority, and
they might as well worship עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, do whatever you
want. דכתיב הכא תועבת ה׳ כל גבה לב—it de-ktiv hacha toavat Hashem
kol geva lev says here, an abomination to God is anyone who
has a, you know, whose heart is raised up, is
haughty—וכתיב התם ולא תביא תועבה אל ביתך, ve-ktiv hatam ve-lo tavi toavah
el beitecha, it's an abomination when you bring in עבודה זרה avodah
zarah to your house. So it's an abomination, it's an equal abomination.
It pulls you away from the authority of
God. רבי יוחנן דידיה אמר—now Rabbi Yochanan didei amar that was Rabbi
Yochanan in the name of his רבי, rebbe, Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai,
but Rabbi Yochanan on his own says: כאילו כפר בעיקר, ke-illu kafar
be-ikar, it's as if you rejected God because actually, which is maybe
a stronger point, because it's, you know, worshipping עבודה זרה avodah zarah
is giving over, rejecting one authority for another;
rejecting God is just an authority unto yourself. שנאמר ורם לבבך ושכחת
את ה׳ אלוהיך, she-ne'emar ve-ram levavecha ve-shachachta et Hashem Elokecha, your heart
will go haughty
and you will forget the Lord your God. Pretty clear that it
is, you know, straight there in the פסוק, pasuk, although of course
the פסוק pasuk is a little bit more like forget that God
is there and helps you, you know, it's not as much of
a direct rejection of God's authority, but they all are related. Okay.
רבי חמא בר חנינא אמר כאילו בא על כל העריות. Rabbi Chama
Bar Chanina amar ke-illu ba al kol ha-arayot. So now getting back
to this argument before that the haughtiness leads to
adultery—and there it was not just the sexual sin, I believe, but
also the fact that it's like you, the man, think you're entitled
to anything, even another man's wife. Here we're just sort of saying
that it leads to
promiscuousness, you'll let your desires reign free, you'll do all of the
עריות. arayot. כתיב הכא תועבת ה׳ כל גבה לב, ktiv hacha toavat
Hashem kol geva lev, abomination to God is all of a haughty
heart, וכתיב התם כי את כל התועבות האלה, ve-ktiv hatam ki et
kol ha-toavot eleh, and it uses the word תועבה toavah to refer
to all of the עריות arayot as a category. עולא אמר כאילו
בנה במה, Ulla amar ke-illu bana bamah, it's as if you built
a במה, bamah, an altar outside of the
בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, שנאמר חדלו לכם מן האדם אשר נשמה באפו
כי במה נחשב. she-ne'emar chidlu lachem min ha-adam asher neshamah be-apo ki
bameh nechshav. You should stop sort of putting your trust in a
human being that the soul is in his nostrils, you know, he
only has the breath of life, he's not God, because how much
value, ultimately, salvation can you get from a man? What is he
worth? במה נחשב הוא. bameh nechshav hu. אל תקרי במה—do al tikri
bameh not read it במה, bameh, "what is," you know, "with what,"
"what is his value"—אלא במה. ella bamah. He is when he is
נשמה באפו, neshamah be-apo, you know, when he sort of is of
haughtiness or maybe the type of person that you would, you know,
think that you should trust him and that all can rely on
him, then he is a במה. bamah. It is as if he
is building his own במה. bamah. Okay, so now, it's interesting the
idea of a במה. bamah. רש״י Rashi says that a במה bamah
would be built on high, would be built on the highest mountains
and the highest places, also lifting himself up. I think it's an
interesting that in conversation with the עבודה זרה avodah zarah and the
כופר בעיקר. kofer be'ikar. עבודה זרה avodah zarah is another god, כופר
בעיקר kofer be'ikar is, you know, is rejecting God completely. Now a
person that's haughty, you know, I think probably we've all seen, met
in our lives, people that are egotistical or haughty and that are
פרום frum and observant and so on. They're not rejecting God, but
they still are somewhat of an authority onto themselves. So what is
the expression of that? Well, that's the במה. bamah. The person says
I'm not going to do what everybody else does, I'm not going
to go ahead and go to the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, I
am going to, you know, do it on my own. I'll still
worship God, but as an authority onto myself. Like a phrase like
everybody is going off and making their own שבת, Shabbos, everybody's deciding
which day is שבת. Shabbos. So, you know, that is the image
of כאילו בנה במה ke'ilu bana bamah as if they have built
a
במה. bamah. Okay, now, יד ליד לא ינקה. yad leyad lo yinakeh.
What is meant by the פסוק pasuk יד ליד לא ינקה? yad
leyad lo yinakeh? Hand to hand will not be clean. That is
the end of the פסוק pasuk before that says that the haughtiness
of the heart is an abomination. So what does this have to
do about
hand to hand? אמר רב, Amar Rav, כל הבא על אשת איש,
kol haba al eshes ish, אפילו הקנהו הקדוש ברוך הוא afilu hiknehu
Hakadosh Baruch Hu שמים וארץ shamayim va'aretz כאברהם אבינו ke'Avraham Avinu דכתיב
ביה dechasiv be הרימתי ידי אל ה׳, harimosi yadi el Hashem, anybody
who has intercourse with a married woman—not exactly clear what this has
to do with a married woman, where did that come from? So
if you take a look at the ב״ח, Bach, the ב״ח Bach
says no, the גרסא girsah is whoever has haughtiness, and that actually
seems to have been the גרסא girsah that רש״י Rashi and others
had. Whoever has haughtiness, even if he is יד ליד, yad leyad,
a hand to God, even if he is somebody that God has
given him over, you know, the mastery of the heaven and
earth, הקדוש ברוך הוא, Hakadosh Baruch Hu, אפילו הקנהו, afilu hiknehu, excuse
me, he has recognized God's mastery over
שמים וארץ shamayim va'aretz כאברהם אבינו ke'Avraham Avinu דכתיב ביה dechasiv be
הרימתי ידי אל ה׳ אל עליון קנה שמים וארץ, harimosi yadi el
Hashem El Elyon koneh shamayim va'aretz, Master of heaven and
earth, לא ינקה מדינה של גיהנום. lo yinakeh midinah shel Gehenom. He
will not be cleansed from the punishment of גיהנום. Gehenom. And here
again, you could think like okay, he's haughty but he recognizes that
God is the Master of all and it's like that's not enough.
Even if you're not like the כופר בעיקר kofer be'ikar and you
recognize God as the Master of all, there is still a problem
of the haughtiness in itself and being the authority onto yourself and
the privileges that you will think and entitlements it will give you
and how you'll relate to other
people. קשיא לדבי רבי שילא. Kashya ledevi Rabi Sheila. So דבי רבי
שילא devei Rabi Sheila did not like this read of the
verse. האי יד ליד לא ינקה, יד מיד מיבעי ליה. Hai yad
leyad lo yinakeh, yad miyad mibayei lei.
Now this is a little bit funny. Somehow, you know, רש״י Rashi
switches, has the גרסא—I girsah read it יד מיד, yad miyad, well
that's actually coming up. רש״י Rashi says the emphasis is ידי, yadei,
right?
יד ליד לא ינקה, יד ידי לא ינקה Yad leyad lo yinakeh,
yad yadei lo yinakeh because, excuse me, ידי לא ינקה, yadi lo
yinakeh, my hand, because if you want to do allude to the
פסוק pasuk by אברהם Avraham rather than saying יד ליד, yad leyad,
it should have said ידי, yadi, like אברהם Avraham says הרימתי ידי,
harimosi yadi, I've lifted up my hand. אלא Ela so, actually that
was a very powerful read I thought, but he is rejecting it
because of
that, אלא אמרי דבי רבי שילא, ela amri devei Rabi Sheila, אפילו
קיבל תורה כמשה רבינו afilu kibel Torah keMoshe Rabbeinu דכתיב ביה dechasiv
be even if this person has so invested themselves in תורה Torah
as and in תורה Torah it is written מימינו אש דת למו
miymino esh das lamo from God's hand it is
a—he is given this fiery law to his people, לא ינקה מדינה
של גיהנום. lo yinakeh midinah shel Gehenom. Even though he has all
of this תורה, Torah, if you have this haughtiness, you know, and
the תורה Torah maybe will lead to a sense of haughtiness, you
will not be cleansed from the punishment of גיהנום. Gehenom. קשיא לרבי
יוחנן Kashya le-Rabbi Yochanan האי יד ליד, יד מיד מיבעי ליה. hai
yad leyad, yad miyad mibayei lei. I was jumping ahead. So רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says no, if it was about hand, God hand
giving us the תורה Torah to our hands, then it should have
said יד מיד, yad miyad, not יד ליד. yad leyad. אלא אמר
רבי יוחנן, Ela amar Rabbi Yochanan, let's try this. What is יד
ליד? yad leyad? That you are not the receiver, but the giver,
your יד yad to somebody else's
יד. yad. אפילו עושה צדקה בסתר, Afilu oseh tzedakah baseser, even if
you do צדקה tzedakah in, you know, in private, in secret. Nobody
knows about it. You're not the one that's putting your name on
buildings, you're anonymous, nobody knows, you respect the dignity of the person,
that's actually a type of behavior that we associate with the opposite
of people that are haughty. So you are both—somebody does both, you
know, they do the צדקה tzedakah exactly the way it should be,
but nevertheless they still go around with their haughtiness and their גסות
הרוח, gasus haruach, so nevertheless—and that we know is hand to a
hand—דכתיב מתן בסתר יכפר אף, dechasiv matan baseser yichaper af, even when
we know that giving in secret and in a way that's respectful,
that's not publicizing it, that's keeping the person's privacy, that that will
cover up the anger of God. Nevertheless, the sin of haughtiness is
so great that לא ינקה מדינה של גיהנום lo yinakeh midinah shel
Gehenom will not be saved from the punishment of גיהנום. Gehenom. So
there's a power of the first two—the first and the last way
of interpreting it. Somebody can be haughty and still recognize the authority
of God. Somebody can be haughty and still do these amazing things
without getting credit for them, and that does not neutralize the problem
of the haughtiness.
Okay, now we continue. אזהרה לגסות הרוח מניין. Azhara legasut haruach minayin.
Now you're going on and on about the problem of this haughtiness,
where do we know that the Torah says that a person shouldn't
be haughty? I mean you have all these פסוקים psukim in משלי
Mishlei that clearly talk against it, but is there any sense that
we can see like a type of a prohibition, shall not, relating
to this? So
אמר רבא ואיתימא רבי זירא, Amar Rava ve'iteima Rabbi Zeira, שמעו והאזינו
אל תגבהו. Shimu veha'azinu al tigbahu. Listen and give ear, do not
lift up, do not raise up. So that's a little general. Also
not a פסוק pasuk in the
Torah, a פסוק pasuk in ירמיהו. Yirmiyahu. רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר
מהכא, Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak amar mehacha, ורם לבבך ושכחת. Veram levavecha
veshachachta. You know, watch yourself lest you know your heart grow lift
up and you forget the Lord your God. So the simple reader
of the verse is you watch yourself lest it leads to you
to forget God. But he is reading watch yourself lest you let
your heart grow grow you know grow high, you know let yourself
become overly
proud. וכתיב השמר לך פן תשכח את ה׳ אלקיך. Uchtiv Hishamer lecha
pen tishkach et Hashem Elokecha. And it says
watch yourself lest you forget the Lord your God. So so therefore
the since the getting of the heart to get to get haughty
leads to forgetting God, getting haughty itself is a form of transgressing
the prohibition of not forgetting God. So I think I misstated it
a minute ago, it's not that the פסוק pasuk says don't let
your heart grow lest your heart grow haughty, but here it says
lest you forget the Lord your
God. Okay. ואמר רבי אבין אמר רבי אילעא Ve'amar Rabbi Avin amar
Rabbi Ila דאמר רבי אבין אמר רבי אילעא da'amar Rabbi Avin amar
Rabbi Ila כל מקום שנאמר השמר פן ואל אינו אלא בלא תעשה.
kol makom shene'emar Hishamer pen ve'al eino ela belo ta'aseh. Wherever it
says you know lest watch yourself shall not, that means that it
is a negative prohibition. So it is not a watch yourself lest
your heart grow haughty, but it is a but it is watch
yourself lest you forget God and since those two are connected, that
is the prohibition for allowing yourself to become
haughty. Okay. דרש רב עוירא Darash Rav Avira זימנין אמר לה משמיה
דרב אסי וזימנין אמר לה משמיה דרב אמי. zimnin amar lah mishmei
deRav Assi vezimnin amar lah mishmei deRav Ami. So רב עוירא Rav
Avira said times some again sometimes in the name of רב אמי,
Rav Ami, sometimes in the name of
רב אסי. Rav Assi. כל אדם שיש בו גסות הרוח לסוף מתמעט.
Kol adam sheyesh bo gasut haruach lisof mitma'et. Whoever has haughtiness you
know you know the you know it's the sort of the what
is it the something before the fall. Anyway, you know and so
whoever has the haughtiness in the end will become
will be lowered down, will be brought down. שנאמר רומו מעט. Shene'emar
romu me'at. You know, lift up a little. And he's reading it,
you know, if you lift yourself up, then you would become מעט,
me'at, you will become a
little. ושמא תאמר ישנו בעולם. Veshema tomar yeshno ba'olam. Okay, come down
a little bit, you're a little bit cut down to size, but
maybe still be somebody that has an impact in the world? תלמוד
לומר ואיננו. Talmud lomar ve'einenu. It'll be as if they never were.
So the punishment for the haughtiness is that you will be cut
down and your memory will be forgotten. ואם חוזר בו נאסף בזמנו
כאברהם אבינו. Ve'im chozer bo ne'esaf bizmano ke'Avraham Avinu. Now I said
your memory be forgotten but from the next line it seems actually
that it's saying that you will actually die suddenly. Because now it
is saying because if the person though does תשובה, teshuva, then they
will live a full life just like
אברהם אבינו Avraham Avinu did. שנאמר והומכו ככל יקפצון. Shene'emar vehumchu kechol
yikfatzun.
So this is the end of the previous פסוק pasuk about
from איוב Iyov that was lift up a little bit. And the
the literal meaning is that they will be brought low, those people
who lift themselves up will be brought low, they'll be gathered in
like everyone else. Meaning don't grow so high high and mighty, in
the end you will die just like everyone else. But now we
are reading it as תשובה. teshuva. You know, if you if you
are mighty then make yourself proud ואיננו, ve'einenu, you'll die suddenly, you'll
die before your time. But if הומכו, humchu, if you make yourself
lowly, you humble yourself and you do תשובה, teshuva, then you will
be gathered in ככל. kechol. What's the ככל? kechol? Like the
everything. כאברהם יצחק ויעקב דכתיב בהו בכל מכל כל. ke'Avraham Yitzchak veYaakov
dechtiv behu bakol mikol kol. Like everybody knows from benching. You'll be
like אברהם יצחק ויעקב Avraham Yitzchak veYaakov that lived a nice long
life and by them it says בכל מכל וכל. bakol mikol vekol.
You could look at רש״י, Rashi, you know, where that words are
by each one of them. So if you make yourself humble and
you do תשובה, teshuva, then you will live a good long life.
ואם לאו, Ve'im lav, but if
not, וכראש שיבולת ימלו uchrosh shibolet yimalu that is the end of
the פסוק, pasuk, like the top of the of
the of the of the wheat, the husk, you will you will
wither away. Okay, so that's the end of the פסוק. pasuk.
So now we're going to look at that piece a little bit.
מאי כראש שיבולת? Mai kerosh shibolet? What like of interpretation can we
give about this sense about the the head of the husk? You
know, they have those like hairs that come out you know as
a crown sort of coming out from the from the top of
the husk of
wheat. רב הונא ורב חסדא חד אמר כיסא דשיבלתא. Rav Huna veRav
Chisda chad amar kisa deshivalta.
Exactly this, it is like the like the hairs that come out
from the top of the husk.
That's
one. וחד אמר כשיבולת עצמה. Vechad amar keshibolet atzmah. No, like the
husk itself. The head of the husk, not something separate from the
husk, but the top of the husk
itself. בשלמא למאן דאמר כיסא דשיבלתא. Bishlama leman de'amar kisa deshivalta. If
you say that it means like the the crown, the hairs from
the top on the top of the husk.
So... היינו דכתיב וכראש שבולת, hainu deksiv ukerosh shiboles, the head, that's
something, that's what this head is, it's this distinct
thing. אלא למאן דאמר כשבולתא עצמה, ela lemandeh amar kishibolta atzma, but
if it's the husk
itself, מאי כראש שבולתא? mai kerosh shibolta? אמר רב אסי וכן תנא
דבי רבי ישמעאל, amar rav asi vechen tana devei rabbi yishmael, משל
לאדם שנכנס לתוך שדהו, mashal leadam shenichnas letoch sado, גבוה גבוה הוא
מלקט. gavoha gavoha hu melaket. Because it means the stuff that is
the tallest, you're walking into the field and you'll gather up, you
know, you'll pick the stuff that rises up at the top. I
mean, maybe, you think about a tree, it's the opposite, the stuff
that's lowest down and closest to you, but it's the one that
draws attention and the stuff that you cut and that you pick
first. So here too, the same way, you know, the first image
was those hairs are cut away and if you make yourself try
to get so high, you know, raising yourself up above, you'll be
cut away like those hairs of the husk. Here, the image is
I think less powerful. You will be cut down like the tall
husks. The tall husks are apparently cut down
first. Okay. ואת דכא ושפל רוח ve'es daka ushefal ruach and now
we are looking at a פסוק pasuk that speaks about, you know,
about God and about God's concern for the humble, that I God
am with the one that is downtrodden and lonely of soul. רב
הונא ורב חסדא. Rav Huna veRav Chisda. So there's a debate of
רב הונא ורב חסדא Rav Huna veRav Chisda just like there was
in the previous פסוק, pasuk, so it's all within the same theme
and it's also רב הונא ורב חסדא. Rav Huna veRav Chisda. חד
אמר איתי דכא, chad amar iti daka, the one that is downtrodden
is with me, I will bring him up to me. וחד אמר
אני את דכא, vechad amar ani es daka, no I will lower
myself and I will be with the one that is downtrodden. Certainly
the more simple read of the
פסוק. pasuk. ומסתברא כמאן דאמר אני את דכא, umistavra kemandeh amar ani
es daka, and it makes sense that it says I will lower
the I will be there with the
downtrodden. שהרי הקדוש ברוך הוא הניח כל הרים וגבעות והשרה שכינתו על
הר סיני. sheharei hakadosh baruch hu hiniach kol harim ugevatos vehishra shechinaso
al har sinai. Because we know, you know, הר סיני, Har Sinai,
the classic statement of חז"ל, chazal, that it was lower than the
mountains and God abandoned all the others and God is willing to
lower God's self to be with the
lowly.
ולא גבה הר סיני למעלה velo gavah har sinai lemala and God
did not lift up הר סיני Har Sinai above, God came down
to הר סיני. Har Sinai. So and that's also I think the
more powerful metaphor when people are feeling lowly and you know and
bleak and in and depressed, they want to feel that God is
present with them there, in their bleakness, in their depression, in their
darkness, not that oh God is going to lift you know you
up. You don't know at that's you know what in the future,
maybe it could be you don't believe that or it's not relevant,
not how you're feeling right now. Now you at all certainly don't
believe it, but to believe that God is with you where you
are right
now. Okay. אמר רב יוסף לעולם ילמד אדם מדעת קונו. amar rav
yosef le'olam yilmad adam mida'as kono. A person should always learn from
the way his creator or her creator made
him, her. שהרי הקדוש ברוך הוא הניח כל הרים וגבעות והשרה שכינתו
על הר סיני. sheharei hakadosh baruch hu hiniach kol harim ugevatos vehishra
shechinaso al har sinai. God left all the mountains and decided to
lower God's self on הר סיני, Har Sinai, the lower one, and
therefore we should act in the same. And another version of this
has
והניח כל אילנות טובות והשרה שכינתו בסנה. vehiniach kol ilanos tovos vehishra
shechinaso basneh. Also was in the lowly thorn bush and not in
some like you know high
trees. אמר רבי אלעזר כל אדם שיש בו גסות הרוח. amar rabbi
elazar kol adam sheyesh bo gasus haruach. Back to haughtiness. Whoever has
in him this haughtiness, ראוי לגדעו כאשרה rauy legade'o ke'asheira is deserving
to be cut down. So before we sort of said God will
cut him down, he'll be cut down before his time. Now we're
sort of saying even harsher things, which is a little disturbing I
must admit, because it's sort of like directed to people, you know,
you should try to cut him down, cut him down to size.
He is he is fit to be cut down to size. You
know, I don't feel that that's necessarily a
helpful dynamic to be putting in the air in between people, but
okay. He certainly is deserving. Let's say God deserving that it come
from God. But that's not what it says.
Okay.
כתיב הכא ורמי הקומה גדועים ksiv hacha veramei hakoma geduim and those
that are high up will be cut
down. וכתיב התם ואשריהם תגדעון. uchsiv hasam va'asheihem tigade'un. So not just
that and their you know and their אשרות Asherot you should chop
down when you enter into the land. So and that is now
the combination of the two words תגדעון tigade'un is not just they
will be cut down, but they should be cut down, you shall
cut them down.
Again, it's interesting and disturbing to think about what the practical implications
are of this that he might be suggesting. Okay. אמר רבי אלעזר
כל אדם שיש בו גסות הרוח אין עפרו ננער. amar rabbi elazar
kol adam sheyesh bo gasus haruach ein afro ninar. Whoever has a
haughtiness, his at his his dust when he know he dies and
decomposes and that's to the פסוק pasuk back in איוב, Iyov, in
the end we're all going to meet the same fate, that will
not be disturbed in the time of תחיית המתים. techiyas hamaysim. So
you know first already it's evoking the idea that you are dust
like all of us and you made yourself so great, in the
end you became dust and you will not even rise up. Not
only that, you know, you won't even be it won't even like
move at that time, שנאמר shenemar but
okay. הקיצו ורננו שוכני עפר. hakitzu veranenu shochnay afar.
Wake up and rejoice those who dwell in the with the dust.
שוכבי בעפר לא נאמר. shochvay be'afar lo ne'emar. It doesn't say those
that have laid down in the dust, which would refer to all
dead people. אלא שוכני עפר. ela shochnay afar. Those that are are
are living among the dust, have been have made neighbor with the
dust. לשכון lishkon is like to dwell in
the. person that was dwelling in the dust in his life, in
his own life when he was
dwelling, was lowly and not was raised up, that person will be
resuscitated at the time of תחיית המתים. Techiyat Hametim.
Okay.
Where were we?
Okay. ואמר רבי אלעזר, v'amar Rabbi Elazar, it says
Rabbi Elazar, כל אדם שיש בו גסות הרוח שכינה מיללת עליו, kol
adam she'yesh bo gasut haruach shechinah mialelat alav, whoever has this
haughtiness of soul, the
Divine Presence wails over him, here you are, you think you're so
amazing, you're just a human being, and what about God and where's
your humility and the Divine Presence wails over the way that this
person just is acting in this
world. מיללת עליו, mialelat alav, שנאמר וגבוה ממרחק יידע, shene'emar v'gavoha mimerchak
yeida, and the High One will be known from a distance, so
means that you could even hear, he's reading it as that you'll
even know the God's wailing can be heard from a distance.
Okay. רבי אבירא ואיתימא רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Avira v'itma Rabbi Elazar, בוא
וראה שלא כמידת הקדוש ברוך הוא מידת בשר ודם, bo u're shelo
kemidat Hakadosh Baruch Hu midat basar vadam, come and see that the
ways of God are not like the ways of flesh and blood.
מידת בשר ודם, midat basar vadam, the ways of flesh and blood,
גבוה רואה את הגבוה, gavoha ro'eh et hagavoha, the high one sees
the high one, people in high office will only see other people
of their rank.
ואין גבוה רואה את השפל, v'ein gavoha ro'eh et hashafal, and the
high will not see people of lowly office and that are seen
as beneath them in the
socioeconomic hierarchy. אבל מידת הקדוש ברוך הוא אינו כן, aval midat Hakadosh
Baruch Hu eino ken, God is not that way. הוא גבוה ורואה
את השפל, hu gavoha v'ro'eh et hashafal, He is high up and
He specifically is out there looking for those who are
lowly. שנאמר כי רם ה' ושפל יראה, shene'emar ki ram Hashem v'shafal
yireh, God is high up and God looks at those that are
lowly. And that actually is in a couple of פסוקים psukim it
really emphasizes
God's tremendous transcendence from the world and how high and mighty God
is. And God, therefore, what do you do with that power? You
don't ignore those that are lowly and marginalized, that is specifically the
responsibility to pay attention to
them. Okay. אמר רב חסדא ואיתימא מר עוקבא, amar Rav Chisda v'itma
Mar Ukva, כל אדם שיש בו גסות הרוח אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא
אין אני והוא יכולים לדור בעולם. kol adam she'yesh bo gasut haruach
amar Hakadosh Baruch Hu ein ani v'hu yecholim lador ba'olam. Somebody who
has this haughtiness, God says, I and he cannot live in the
same world because if you're haughty you fill up all the space
and you're the only authority. Well, if you're the only authority, excuse
me, I'm leaving here. Okay. We both can't live in the same
space. שנאמר מלשני בסתר רעהו, shene'emar malshni baseter re'ehu, the
one who
libels, who tells evil speech in
private against his friend, אותו אצמית, oto azmit, he I will cut
down, גבה עיניים ורחב לבב, gvah einayim u'rchav levav, the one who
is of high eyes, that's this second part is the part that's
relevant to us, and of wide heart, אותו לא אוכל. oto lo
uchal. Him I shall not,
him I will not suffer, I can't be, I can't
tolerate him. So that's אותו לא אוכל, oto lo uchal, that's the
simple meaning of the פסוק, pasuk, but he's going to read it
the following way. אל תקרי אותו לא אוכל אלא איתו לא אוכל.
al תקרי oto lo uchal ela ito lo uchal. I can't be
with him. Okay. If he's filling up the space and he's everything,
then thank you, I'm
leaving. איכא דמתני לה אמספרי לשון הרע. ika d'matni lah amsaprei lashon
hara. Now, some will look at that about the first half of
the פסוק, pasuk, the second half speaks about haughtiness of eye, but
the first part speaks about the לשון הרע lashon hara and maybe
the sin that the פסוק pasuk is focusing on is the לשון
הרע lashon hara that comes from that haughtiness and not the haughtiness
itself. אמספרי לשון הרע, amsaprei lashon hara, שנאמר מלשני בסתר רעהו אותו
אצמית. shene'emar malshni baseter re'ehu oto azmit. Okay. אמר רבי אלכסנדרי, amar
Rabbi Alexandri, כל אדם שיש בו גסות הרוח אפילו רוח קימעא עוכרתו,
kol adam she'yesh bo gasut haruach afilu ruach kima ocharto, whoever has
this haughtiness of spirit, even a little spirit, even a little wind
will upset him like make the waters, like a little breeze will
make all the waters turbulent. People that are very focused on their
own status are hypersensitive to little tiny little slights and things that
they think could be
possibly slighting their status and people not realizing their authority. Okay. Even
a little
one. שנאמר והרשעים כים נגרש, shene'emar v'hareshaim k'yam nigrash, and the wicked
are like the ocean are driven out.
ומה ים שיש בו כמה רביבות רוח קימעא עוכרתו. u'mah yam she'yesh
bo kama revivot ruach kima ocharto. The ocean, it has many, many
quarts of water in it, it's enormously large. And nevertheless a little
wind can disturb the calmness of the sea.
So if that's true, אדם שאין בו אלא רביעית, adam she'ein bo
ela revit, a human being that only has a רביעית revit of
blood in him, which is the
גמרא's Gemara understanding, רביעית אחת על אחת כמה וכמה, revit achat al
achat kama v'chama, how much more so will this little, will this
little wind disturb him. And obviously
not every human being, those that are labeled רשעים, reshaim, which we
now are identifying as those of
haughtiness. אמר רבי חייא בר אשי אמר רב, amar Rabbi Chiya bar
Ashi amar Rav, תלמיד חכם צריך שיהא בו אחד משמיני שבשמינית. talmid
chacham tzarich she'yehe bo echad mishmini shebishminit. So a תלמיד חכם talmid
chacham has to have an eighth of an eighth,
1/64 of.
of haughtiness, you know, because you need a certain sense of self-respect
for the תורה Torah and if somebody slights you, they're also slighting
the תורה Torah that you represent. So a little bit, a little
bit of גאוה, gaiva, you know, is a tiny tiny bit. Not—he
didn't say one sixty-fourth, an eighth of an eighth, a derivative of
a derivative. It's interesting why he said an eighth, I don't know
but anyway, but that amount can be tolerated. Two degrees removed. That
amount can be tolerated. Now you remember before the גמרא Gemara says
if you have haughtiness, even if somebody who is like they received
the תורה Torah from הר סיני, Har Sinai, right, will—will not be
cleansed from גיהנום. Gehennom. So תורה Torah can
bring—can—you know, that—it can bring way too much haughtiness with it. And
that's a real danger. But also don't be so humble that you
don't have a sense of the תורה Torah that you
represent. אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע ומעטרה ליה כי סאסא לשבולתא.
Amar Rav Huna brei de-Rav Yehoshua, u-ma’atra lei ke-sasa l’shibulta. So and
it crowns him like the—like the hairs on top of the husk
of corn. You'll remember that that was the פסוק pasuk before that
said those hairs will be cut off. But here it's saying, you
know, that actually a little bit actually adorns you and gives you
the right type of pride that brings honor.
So here's—but of course one cannot forget
the—not—not invoke the other פסוק. pasuk. So—so it has the potential of
being
dangerous. אמר רבא בשמתא דאית ביה ובשמתא דלית ביה. Amar Rava: Beshamta
de-is bei u-v’shamta de-leis bei. Rava said this is—it is too dangerous.
Somebody should be in חרם cherem if you have גאוה, gaiva, a
תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, and should be in חרם cherem if you
don't have גאוה. gaiva. Meaning, like, it's a—it's a very delicate line,
you know, to tread. A little too much and you're deserving of
being in חרם cherem because, you know,
you—the תורה Torah is supposed to make us sensitive to people and
humble to people, not lord it over. And at the same time,
if you have too little, then also you're not properly representing the
תורה Torah that—and the authority of the תורה. Torah. So it's a
very—very delicate and impossible balance. Okay. You know, now אמר רב נחמן
בר יצחק. amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak. Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak says,
'I'm going to solve this for you. לא מינה ולא מקצתה. Lo
minah v’lo miktzatah. I don't want to have anything to do with
it and I don't want anything to do with even the tiniest
bit of it.' מי זוטר דכתיב ביה? Mi zutar de-chsiv bei? Is
it—you know, is it—is it of naught? Is it little when the
פסוק pasuk says to it: תועבת ה׳ כל גבה לב? Toavat Hashem
kol g’vah lev? An abomination to God. So if it's an abomination
to God, we need to keep a mile away from it. Now,
abomination to God is when your heart is lifted up. You know,
is there a way that you can have some of that מדה
middah without it leading to גבהות לב? gavhus lev? But he just
says it is way too dangerous. So this has a whole interesting
thing, you know, about how some תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim are super
humble, they're—you know, some of the more interesting stories are about ones
that were arrogant or quite arrogant. So a lot to be reflecting
on here. Classic joke in the ישיבה yeshiva is, 'Oh yes, you
know, he—the גמרא Gemara says he should have an eighth eighth of
an arrogance, but as with other things, he's just very מחמיר machmir
on the שיעור.' shiur. So anyway, that is definitely a challenge in
both directions and as the גמרא—sort Gemara of the thrust of the
גמרא, Gemara, too often our problem is the people that have—being too
מחמיר, machmir, are having too much of it, not too
little. Okay. אמר חזקיה אין תפלתו של אדם נשמעת אלא אם כן
משים לבו כבשר. Amar Chizkiyah: Ein tefilaso shel adam nishma'as ela im
kein mesim libo k’vasar. Now we're going to talk about the value
of being humble. Your—person's prayer is only heard if he makes his
heart like flesh, not like stone, not like a spirit lifted up,
but humble, like flesh, flexible like
flesh. שנאמר והיה מדי חדש בחדשו יבוא כל בשר להשתחוות. Shene'emar: Vehayah
midei chodesh be-chodsho yavo kol basar le-hishtachavos. All flesh will come, you
know, to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash in the future. If you
treat yourself as flesh and bones and as human and as flexible
and as, you know, an impression can be made, that—that's the type
of person whose prayer God wants to
hear. אמר רבי זירא בשר כתיב ביה ונרפא. Amar Rabbi Zeira: Basar
kesiv bei v’nerpa. When it talks about the צרעת, tzara’as, the skin
disease, when it speaks about, you know, it comes on the flesh,
it says if there's a—if there's a צרעת tzara'as on the flesh,
it says it will
heal. אדם לא כתיב ביה ונרפא. Adam lo kesiv bei v’nerpa. When
it says if a אדם, adam, a person, has this צרעת, tzara'as,
it does not use the פסוק pasuk when it says 'it will
heal'. Obviously, it could clear up. But the point is, you know,
when you think about אדם, adam, you're a person, you know, man,
you represent—you know, human, you know, there's a sense of a certain
sense of pride and so on. If that's how you're thinking about
yourself, it's hard for you to heal and to change and to
listen to see what's wrong. Whereas if you treat yourself like flesh,
healing is much more possible. אמר רבי יוחנן. Amar Rabbi Yochanan. Rabbi
Yochanan says you—we should always be sort of like aware of what's
embedded in the word אדם. adam. A man is—can be read as
an acronym: אפר דם מרה. Eifer, dam, marah. Ashes, like dust and
ashes, blood, and bile. בשר: Basar: בושה סרוחה רמה. bushah, sruchah, rimah.
בשר Basar is embarrassment, you know, spoiling, and—and maggots. So now it's
not the benefit of בשר basar over אדם, adam, just remember that
we're all flesh and blood. איכא דאמרי *Ikka d'amri* שאול שאול *Sheol
Sheol* excuse me the depths the netherworld that's where we're all going
instead of the instead of the סרוחה *srucha* spoiled which is reading
a ס *samech* for a ש *sin* here we're going to read
a ש *shin* for a ש *sin* דכתיב בשין *dich'tiv b'shin*. אמר
רב אשי כל אדם שיש בו גסות הרוח לסוף נפחת *Amar Rav
Ashi kol adam sheyesh bo gasut haruach lisof nifchat*. Anybody who has
that haughtiness of the soul in the end will be brought down
and made lowly. שנאמר
ולשאת ולספחת *Shene'emar u'laseit v'lasapachat*. These are the types of leprosy and
the word שאת *se'eit* means these are just names of them but
the דרשה *derasha* is ואין שאת אלא לשון גבוה *ve'ein se'eit ela
lashon gavo'ah*. שאת *Se'eit* means lifted up. שנאמר ועל כל ההרים הרמים
ועל כל הגבעות הנישאות *Shene'emar ve'al kol heharim haramim ve'al kol hageva'ot
hanisa'ot* right the mountains that are lifted up. ואין ספחת אלא טפלה
*Ve'ein sapachat ela tfeilah*. ספחת *Sapachat* means something that is secondary that
is adhering on something lowly. שנאמר ספחני נא אל אחת הכהונות לאכול
פת לחם *Shene'emar saphcheini na el achat hakehunot le'echol pat lechem* sort
of like gather me in you know that I should eat some
bread. אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי בא וראה כמה גדולים נמוכי הרוח
לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא *Amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi bo ur'ei kama
gdolim nemuchei haruach lifnei Hakadosh Baruch Hu*. Come and see how great
are those of lowly spirit before God. שבשעה שבית המקדש קיים אדם
מקריב עולה שכרה בידו *Shebesha'ah sheBeit HaMikdash kayam adam makriv olah schara
beyado*. When there was a בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash* if a person
brought an עולה *olah* great you get the merit of bringing an
עולה *olah*. מנחה שכר
מנחה בידו *Mincha schar mincha beyado*. If you bring a מנחה *mincha*
you get the merit of bringing a מנחה *mincha*. אבל מי שדעתו
שפלה מעלה עליו הכתוב כאילו הקריב כל הקרבנות כולם *Aval mi sheda'ato
shfeilah ma'aleh alav hakatuv ke'ilu hikriv kol hakorbanot kulam*. But somebody who
had a lowly spirit it's as if he brought all the sacrifices
even when there was a בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash* and you could
have brought sacrifices and that was a possibility if you have the
lowly spirit it's better than people you know now you're as good
as a person who brought sacrifices you're as if you brought all
the sacrifices that is absolute the best that I want more than
I want anybody's sacrifice okay. שנאמר כדכתיב זבחי
אלהים רוח נשברה *Shene'emar kid'chtiv zivchei Elokim ruach nishbarah*. The
sacrifices in plural of God is a broken spirit. ולא עוד אלא
שאין תפילתו נמאסת *Velo od ela she'ein tfilato nima'eset*. His prayer will
not be
despised a little bit funny you know how after saying all the
sacrifices seems like this is a little anticlimactic but anyway. שנאמר לב
נשבר ונדכה אלהים לא תבזה *Shene'emar lev nishbar v'nidkeh Elokim lo tivzeh*.
A broken and a lowly heart God will not despise. ואמר רבי
יהושע בן לוי כל השם אורחותיו בעולם הזה *Ve'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi kol hasham orchotav ba'olam hazeh*. Okay anybody who weighs their acts
in this world this is actually a little bit of a shift
from what we were talking about like שומא *shuma* שומא *shuma*'s like
an estimation of בית דין *Beit Din* meaning so this רמב"ם *Rambam*
quotes this statement of רבי יהושע בן לוי *Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi*
about he says the core religious principle like the guiding principle in
life is יהיו כל מעשיך לשם שמים *yehiu kol ma'asecha leshem shamayim*.
Everything you do you should be assessing why am I doing this
and you should be weighing it and assessing it לשם שמים *leshem
shamayim*. So he says a pretty high standard so רבי יהושע בן
לוי *Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi* says whoever basically weighs and assesses his
actions his paths maybe your general direction maybe not every single movement
in this world זוכה ורואה בישועתו של הקדוש ברוך הוא *zocheh v'ro'eh
bishu'ato shel Hakadosh Baruch Hu* will see in the salvation of God.
שנאמר ושם דרך אראנו בישע אלהים *Shene'emar vesham derech areinu beyesha Elokim*
and I will place my you know the path and I will
see in the salvation. והוא אמר אל תקרי ושם *Vehu amar al
tikrei vesham* the one who places or orders his path אלא ושם
דרך *ela vesham derech* one who assesses and weighs and evaluates his
actions. Okay very long passage about arrogance and humility fascinating thing about
the תלמיד חכם *talmid chacham* and the two directions about that but
I also think רוח רוח רוח *ruach ruach ruach* here lined up
against עברה עליו רוח קנאה *avrah alav ruach kinah* and how you
know I think that there is a real juxtaposition intended juxtaposition about
what is that spirit that is leading this man to be jealous
about his wife. Okay so now we are going to continue back
to the הלכה *halacha* and back to the משנה mishnah: *mishna*. כיצד
מקנא לה *Keitzad m'kanei lah*? How does he give do this קינוי
*kinui* this warning? And חז"ל *Chazal* here have turned this קינוי *kinui*
you know turned the whole thing into a more of a legal
process and taken it out in the פסוקים *psukim*. The Torah the
man has an enormous amount of latitude and authority but the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* brings in עדים *eidim* and בית דין *Beit Din* and
makes it all legalized it and much much limited it the husband's
authority. So and he says how do you warn in front of
one witness or two witnesses depending on the debate you know warn
her not to be in private with a certain person. But the
example in the משנה *mishna* is he warns her don't speak to
a man and then it says and if she speaks to a
man she is permitted until she is in private with a man.
Okay so she has to be in private that's the action but
what's his warning is that don't speak or is that don't be
in private? It would seem it would have to be don't be
in private but the משנה *mishna* doesn't say that so that's what
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* deals with. הגופא קשיא *Ha gupa kashya* this
is internally contradictory. אמרת אמר לה בפני שנים אל תדברי al tedabri
עם איש פלוני זה *Amarta amar lah bifnei shnayim al tdabri im
ish ploni zeh* he says in front of two witnesses do not
speak to this man specific man. אלמא דיבור dibbur סתירה הוא *Alma
dibur stirah hu* so you see that speaking to a person to
a man is equivalent הלכתית *halachit* to being in private with him.
for the laws of
סוטה. והדר תני ve-hadar tanya דברה עמו עדיין מותרת לביתה dibrah imo
adayin muteret le-veitah מותרת לאכול בתרומה. muteret leechol bi-trumah. But if she
speaks with the man, even if she was warned not to, she
remains permissible to having sex with her husband, that's what לביתה le-veitah
means, and to eat תרומה trumah for her husband's a כהן. kohen.
אלמא דיבור לאו כלום הוא. alma dibbur lav klum hu. The דיבור
speech is not the problem, problem is being in private. So shouldn't
the warning have to match the act that creates the problem? Now,
you could of course say no, the warning could be any warning,
but it's not a problem until she violates it so much to
the point that it's possible she had sex with the man. But
the גמרא is not reading it that way. And the גמרא says
אמר אביי הכי קאמר, amar Abaye hachi ka-amar, here's how you have
to read the משנה: אל תדברי ודברה, ve-dibra, if he says don't
speak to this man and she spoke, אל תדברי ונסתרה al tedabri
ve-nistera or don't speak and she went into
private, אל תסתרי ודברה עמו al tisteri ve-dibra imo or don't go
in private and she spoke to
him, עדיין מותרת לביתה מותרת לאכול בתרומה. adayin muteret le-veitah muteret le-echol
bi-trumah. She still permissible to her husband, to eat תרומה. trumah. None
of those makes her forbidden because you don't have either the warning
in place or the act, you know, the warning correct or the
act correct quote-unquote. Okay,
however, נכנסה עמו לבית הסתר ושהת כדי טומאה אסורה לביתה ואסורה לאכול
בתרומה. nichnesa imo le-veit ha-seter ve-shahat kedei tumah asura le-veitah va-asura le-echol
bi-trumah. עדיין מותרת לביתה מותרת לאכול בתרומה, adayin muteret le-veitah muteret le-echol
bi-trumah, נכנסה—but, nichnesa in that last case when he said don't go
in private, for in that
case, נכנסה עמו לבית הסתר, nichnesa imo le-veit ha-seter, if after being
warned not to be in private she goes into a private place,
ושהת כדי טומאה ve-shahat kedei tumah and she waits the time it's
possible to have intercourse, אסורה לביתה asura le-veitah then she can no
longer have sex with her husband, ואסורה לאכול בתרומה va-asura le-echol bi-trumah
and she can't eat תרומה trumah if she was eating it on
account of her husband being a כהן. kohen. So we will stop
here and pick up at the bottom of עמוד ב' amud bet
tomorrow.